<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Posts</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/</link><description>scott kosman RSS Feed</description><generator>Hugo</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 13:54:55 UTC</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://scottkosman.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>So You're A Manager Now. Part 3: Influencing Without Authority</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now-influence-without-authority/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now-influence-without-authority/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>Sometimes you have to lead people you don't manage.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The first couple posts in this series were about surviving the shock of management. The one-on-ones. The feedback. The “oh god I have so many vacation requests to approve.”</p>
<p>But once you get through that? The game changes. You realize pretty quickly that <strong>you can’t get anything meaningful done by just managing the folks who report to you.</strong></p>
<p>Your team doesn’t own all the code paths. Product has their own priorities. Design has their own calendar. Your boss has opinions. Two different executive stakeholders both want to own your team&rsquo;s roadmap for the next quarter with conflicting demands. Suddenly everything&rsquo;s on fire, the streams are crossing, you can&rsquo;t control <em>any</em> of it, and the idea of letting it all burn to the ground while you go flip burgers at Wendy&rsquo;s seems pretty damn tempting.</p>
<p>Welcome to the part of management nobody warned you about: learning how to influence without authority.</p>
<p>And here’s the truth: every Engineering Manager job interview you’ll ever do will come back to this. It’s one of those “tell me about a time…” questions that separates the rookies from the people who can actually move an org forward.</p>
<center><img src="https://media4.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExdGdvemgxZXNoczR2emdtZ2NyaXE2ZWkxcmhyaGx1d2xsdXBrbDcwbiZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/uQHtUvva9Qljy/giphy.gif" alt="RESPECT MAH AUTHORITAH"></center>
<hr>
<h2 id="why-your-title-doesnt-mean-shit">Why Your Title Doesn’t Mean Shit</h2>
<p>This was a tough lesson for me to learn early on in my career: having “manager” in your title doesn’t magically grant you superpowers. People outside your team don’t care about your reporting line. They care about <em>their</em> goals, their deadlines, their pain. If you come in swinging your title around, at <em>best</em> you&rsquo;ll actually get nothing accomplished. At <em>worst</em> you&rsquo;ll start to make <strong>enemies.</strong></p>
<p>I can tell you from stark, painful personal experience how hard that is to recover from.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="tools-i-wish-id-figured-out-earlier">Tools I Wish I’d Figured Out Earlier</h2>
<p>The first tool is <strong>relationships.</strong> People help people they like and trust, and there’s no shortcut for that. If you only show up when you need something, you won’t get far. You start building this on Management Day #1 (or today!). If you haven’t been working on building trust with your cross-functional partners and positioning yourself as a voice of reason and clarity in the room <em>before</em> shit hits the fan (and it will), you’re going to be in a tough spot.</p>
<p>The second is <strong>framing.</strong> Your idea has to live in other people’s worlds, not just yours. Don’t pitch a logging standard; pitch cutting support tickets in half. Don’t talk about “technical debt”; talk about freeing up capacity for roadmap features. Selling an idea or persuading someone to see your point of view is a hell of a lot more effective when you can position it as something that aligns with their best interests. &ldquo;Help me help you&rdquo; will get you a lot farther than &ldquo;do it my way&rdquo; ever could.</p>
<p>Third, you need to <strong>tell the story.</strong> Humans don’t rally around bullet points and Jira tickets, they rally around a clear <em>why</em>. Nothing will erode your authority faster than coming across like you don&rsquo;t know what you&rsquo;re talking about, so make the fuck sure that you do. Paint a picture that people want to be part of. Keep the receipts. Show your work. Present the data supporting your point of view. Make it crystal-clear why the thing is the <em>right</em> thing. And honestly? If you can&rsquo;t conclusively bring this to the table then maybe what you want to do isn&rsquo;t the right idea after all. There&rsquo;s no shame in realizing that.</p>
<p>And finally, <strong>repetition</strong> matters more than you think. You’ll feel like a broken record long before anyone else has actually absorbed your message. If it’s important, keep saying it until people start repeating it back to you. If you&rsquo;re starting to feel sick of saying the same thing over and over again that just might mean you&rsquo;re on the right track.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="how-i-fucked-this-up-a-sob-story">How I Fucked This Up: A Sob Story</h2>
<p>I hate to shatter the perfect angelic image I’ve so carefully cultivated, but I learned all this the hard way.</p>
<center><img src="https://media1.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExZ2JjeGtlOWhjeDc3N24xd2FiYW1kZnpxajFkY2VmYW16OG0xb2MweSZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/yRqZr5CsHGQxxPXqFC/giphy.gif" alt="Look, if you can't see what this gif is displaying you're probably actually better off." width="300"></center>
<p>Years ago, in a different life and a different industry, I ran all internal and external communications for a megachurch. Church website, print materials, event promotion, radio ads, press releases, the whole noodle. I was young, headstrong, and thought that because I was the DRI for these things, I had the final say in how everything operated and everyone would automatically follow my lead. Shut up, stop laughing.</p>
<p>This all fell apart in spectacular fashion the very first time the music director and the missionary pastor both wanted prime real estate on the church website at the same time. It crumbled further when six different staff members had opinions about a font choice I had used for a Christmas Eve service program. It turned into a smoldering crater when I figured I could just make decisions in a vacuum because I was ✨Responsible✨ only to find angry mobs lined up outside my office demanding their individual pounds of flesh.</p>
<p>In the end, I failed not because I lacked the skills to produce the work. I failed because I hadn&rsquo;t cultivated a single one of the tools mentioned above. I hadn&rsquo;t built relationships, I didn&rsquo;t take the time to learn or assess other people’s wants or needs, I had no idea how to reframe competing options around the organization’s overall goals, and I assumed saying things once was enough. Remember how I said earlier that making enemies is hard to recover from? The only thing I did right in this situation was quit before they could fire me.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="how-to-practice-without-burning-yourself-out">How to Practice Without Burning Yourself Out</h2>
<p>You don’t learn influence by reading about it, you learn it by trying. But trying doesn’t mean pushing every single idea uphill until you’re exhausted. Pick your spots. Start with something small where the stakes are low and you can afford to stumble, like a process tweak or a quality-of-life improvement for your team. Treat each attempt like a rep at the gym: you’re building muscle, not chasing a personal best every time. And when something doesn’t land, don’t take it as a referendum on your leadership. Take the feedback, adjust, and go again. Influence is a long game, and the only way to get better at it is to practice in ways that won’t leave you bitter or burned out.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="why-every-interviewer-will-ask-you-about-this">Why Every Interviewer Will Ask You About This</h2>
<p>If you’ve ever prepped for a management interview, you know the question is coming: <em>“Tell me about a time you influenced without authority.”</em> It shows up in every loop because it is the quickest way to gauge whether you can operate beyond the walls of your own team. Influence without authority is really about <strong>scope</strong>. As an engineering manager, your job is not just to make your team successful, it is to move initiatives forward across teams, disciplines, and sometimes even the entire organization.</p>
<p>At some point, you&rsquo;ll need to convince Product to adjust priorities, persuade Design to tweak scope, get another engineering team to adopt standards, or rally leadership around a technical investment that doesn&rsquo;t have obvious short-term ROI. None of these come with direct authority. What you bring to the table is credibility, clarity, and the ability to create alignment where there was none.</p>
<p>This is exactly why interviewers care. Your ability to influence across boundaries is a proxy for whether you can manage scope at the next level. Scope is <em>messy</em>. It lives in the Venn Diagram overlap between teams. Your engineering team&rsquo;s performance and impact might be dialled in, but if you can only operate at that level you&rsquo;ll eventually hit a ceiling. A manager who can influence across functions is someone an interviewer can imagine leading bigger programs, other managers, and shaping the organization itself.</p>
<center><img src="/influence-venn.png" style="border: 2px black solid" alt="Venn Diagram showing the overlap between Engineering, Product, and Design with the caption 'Surprise! You live in these spaces now.'"></center>
<center><small>Everything's better with a Venn.</small></center>
<hr>
<h2 id="dont-screw-this-up">Don&rsquo;t Screw This Up</h2>
<p>Influence without authority is uncomfortable because it forces you to play the long game. It takes time and energy to build trust in the people around you. You won’t get it right every time, and it’ll feel slower and messier than you want. But every conversation, every nudge, and every relationship you invest in builds leverage for the moments that matter. With practice, influence without authority is what takes you from being just a <strong>manager</strong> who keeps the trains running to a <strong>leader</strong> who can move the whole organization forward.</p>
<p>You don’t get influence by asking nicely. You get it by showing up, doing the work over and over, until no one can ignore you.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Nobody Wins at Calendar Tetris</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/calendar-tetris/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/calendar-tetris/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>The only prizes in Calendar Tetris are burnout and sadness.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="if-tetris-has-taught-me-anything-its-that-errors-pile-up--accomplishments-disappear">&ldquo;If Tetris has taught me anything, it&rsquo;s that errors pile up &amp; accomplishments disappear.&rdquo;</h2>
<p>Most weeks my calendar looks like a game of Tetris. Colored blocks dropping in faster than I can clear them, stacking higher and higher until I’m scrambling just to keep up. One more meeting, one more call, and suddenly the screen’s full. Game over.</p>
<p>Earlier in my career I wore that like a badge of honor. &ldquo;Look how busy I am! Look how important I must be!&rdquo; But here’s the truth: Calendar Tetris isn’t leadership. It’s just chaos dressed up as status.</p>
<p>Busy <em>doesn’t mean effective</em>. It usually means you’ve stopped being intentional with your time. And when your calendar is filling up row by row every week you’re not proving your worth, you’re just proving that you’ve lost control of it.</p>
<center><img src="/calendar_wtf.png" alt="A screenshot of a calendar that is completely packed full of meetings and appointments"></center>
<center><small>"Hey, do you have time for a quick chat?"</small></center>
<p>⸻</p>
<h2 id="the-status-symbol-of-busy">The Status Symbol of Busy</h2>
<p>Somewhere along the way, “busy” became shorthand for “important.” If your calendar isn’t wall-to-wall, people start wondering what you’re even doing. So we keep dropping blocks, meeting after meeting, until the board is jammed.</p>
<p>But being in the room isn’t the same as having impact. Half the time you’re just nodding along while someone else talks, or <em>worse</em>, you&rsquo;re only paying attention with 15% of your brain while you multitask working on something else (which is <em>always</em> the moment someone&rsquo;s going to call on you for something). This is when you need to realize that your FOMO is probably killing you.</p>
<p>And the irony? The higher the stack gets, the less room there is to maneuver. The busier you are, the less your team can actually get done. If you’re the bottleneck in every decision then you’re <strong>not showing value</strong>. You’re just slowing everyone down.</p>
<p>⸻</p>
<h2 id="the-reality-check">The Reality Check</h2>
<p>Here’s the ugly truth: busy doesn’t mean productive. A week packed with meetings might look impressive, but most of the real work gets shoved into the cracks: late nights, early mornings, or (unfortunately and most commonly) not at all. The more you overload yourself, the more you drift into reactive mode. You’re bouncing from block to block, praying for a line clear, and by Friday you realize you didn’t actually move anything forward. You just survived.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the things that actually matter: coaching your team, thinking ahead, and making good decisions get shoved off the board. Nobody remembers how many hours you sat in meetings. They remember whether you cleared the way for them to do great work.</p>
<p>⸻</p>
<h2 id="the-cost-of-the-cult">The Cost of the Cult</h2>
<p>Playing Calendar Tetris comes with a price tag, and it’s steep.</p>
<p>First, you lose the space to think. Strategy doesn’t happen in fifteen-minute gaps between Zoom calls. It needs air. Without it, you make short-term calls that feel urgent but don’t actually solve the real problems.</p>
<p>Second, your team pays the bill. If you’re always stacking blocks, you’re not available when they need you. They either wait for you to come up for air or they guess and hope for the best. Neither option sets them up to succeed.</p>
<p>And finally, there’s burnout—yours and theirs. Hustle culture loves to dress exhaustion up as dedication, but all it really does is drain people until they stop caring. “Always busy” isn’t leadership. It’s a slow-motion collapse.</p>
<p>I’ll be honest: I hit this point myself recently. I’ve got a big team, and I value 1:1s with my ICs more than just about anything but something had to give. That calendar screenshot at the top of the page? That&rsquo;s been my reality every week for far too long. Days of back-to-back-to-back meetings and my calendar being a solid wall of color meant that any focus or planning time I had to myself was happening in the evenings after dinner and that&rsquo;s not healthy or sustainable. For now, I’ve moved my 1:1s to biweekly. I don’t love that. It’s not the manager I want to be long term. But if I kept stacking blocks the way I was, the screen was going to fill up.</p>
<center><img src="/tetris_game_over.png" alt="Tetris game over screen from a Nintendo Game Boy"></center>
<center><small>I make no apologies to those of you too young to have known the Nintendo Game Boy.</small></center>
⸻
<h2 id="escaping-the-game">Escaping the Game</h2>
<p>The way out starts with redefining what “important” looks like. Impact isn’t measured in how many blocks you stacked. It’s measured in whether the lines clear and your team has space to play.</p>
<p>Protect your focus time like it’s a meeting with your CEO. Make it visible. Block it off. And when someone wants to add another call to your week, remember my favorite rule: <strong>no agenda, no attenda.</strong> If people can’t explain why you’re needed, you’re not needed.</p>
<p>Say no more often. Skip the meeting. Delegate. Better yet, build a culture where your team feels empowered to do the same. Nothing sends a stronger signal than a manager who refuses to play Calendar Tetris for the sake of appearances.</p>
<p>Here’s the thing about Tetris: the blocks never stop coming. You can’t win, you can only hold out until you lose.</p>
<h3 id="busy-is-easy-impactful-is-hard">Busy is easy. Impactful is hard.</h3>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Not My Torment Nexus</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/not-my-torment-nexus/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/not-my-torment-nexus/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>From ad agencies to Kanye to almost working in the adult film industry: how I nearly gave up my integrity and found my line.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="how-i-almost-built-the-torment-nexus">How I Almost Built The Torment Nexus</h2>
<center><img src="/torment-nexus.png" alt="at long last we have created the torment nexus"></center>
<p>Like a lot of people, I was laid off at the start of COVID. It was the worst health and economic crisis of my lifetime (so far!), and after a couple of months out of work, the panic set in. I had bills to pay, a family to feed, and no clear end in sight.</p>
<p>So I did something I’m not proud of: I applied for an Engineering Manager job at Pornhub.</p>
<p>That flies in the face of one of my core tests for any job: <em>would I be proud to describe what I do?</em> It still bothers me that I swallowed my integrity that quickly. Obviously I didn’t get the job (I&rsquo;m guessing they noped out when they saw &ldquo;Bachelor of Christian Theology&rdquo; listed amongst my qualifications), but I also didn’t walk away from that moment unchanged. I had crossed my own line, and it forced me to think a lot harder about where that line actually is.</p>
<p>It wasn’t my first time building something I didn’t believe in. Early in my career, I worked in ad agencies with client lists that were a mix of inspiring brands and… not-so-inspiring ones. Sometimes I was tasked with creating products I’d never use or services I didn’t trust, simply because the client was paying for it. Years later I was working at adidas during the height of Kanye West’s increasingly hateful, racist behavior and his very public buddying up to President Trump. I happened to be leading a Yeezy sneaker campaign at the time and boy howdy did that make me feel like ass. It wasn’t the direct reason I left adidas, but it was definitely a factor that made walking away easier when I started debating my future there.</p>
<h2 id="the-foundation-you-build-on">The Foundation You Build On</h2>
<p>We don’t always get to choose perfect work under perfect circumstances but we <strong>do</strong> get to decide what we&rsquo;re willing to attach our name to. The ethos of a company, its values, its real purpose, and the impact it has on the world isn’t just branding fluff. It&rsquo;s the foundation you build on as a leader. If you can’t stand behind it, your team will feel it, even if you never say a word.</p>
<p>Sometimes the misalignment is obvious, like applying for a role you know, deep down, you couldn’t tell your grandmother about without changing the subject halfway through. Other times, it sneaks up on you. You join a company because you believe in what they are building, but over time the ground shifts under your feet. The mission statement doesn’t change, but how it&rsquo;s lived out starts to feel different. Corners get cut. Priorities tilt toward whatever closes the next deal. Conversations about customers turn into conversations about “market capture” and “lifetime value.” You notice that the <em>why</em> behind decisions gets harder to find.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve been in leadership for more than ten seconds you&rsquo;ve maybe already felt this creeping drift. The ethos isn’t gone, it is just bending quietly in ways that are easy to rationalize.</p>
<h3 id="some-early-warning-signs-ive-learned-to-watch-for">Some early warning signs I&rsquo;ve learned to watch for:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Values get reinterpreted to fit short-term wins (“We value transparency… except for this quarter’s roadmap”).</li>
<li>Customers stop being people and start being numbers (“Churn reduction” instead of “Why are they leaving?”).</li>
<li>Known harm gets waved through because &ldquo;the client really really wants it&rdquo; or “we’ll fix it in the next version.”</li>
<li>The “why” disappears, or is replaced with something that sounds more like a sales pitch than a truth.</li>
</ul>
<p>When those signs start piling up, you&rsquo;re no longer just building a product. You&rsquo;re building the Torment Nexus, whether you meant to or not. Like a frog in a pot of heating water (except the water’s a quarterly roadmap and you’re the frog) you might not notice until you’re fully poached.</p>
<p>That doesn&rsquo;t mean you&rsquo;re stuck forever.</p>
<h2 id="the-ethos-test">The Ethos Test</h2>
<p>When I’m figuring out if I can actually get behind where the company’s headed, I boil it down to a few simple questions. Nothing fancy, but they cut through a lot of the noise:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Would I explain this to my family with pride?</strong><br>
If I&rsquo;d dodge the details at the dinner table, that&rsquo;s a red flag.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Does it make customers’ lives better, safer, or easier?</strong><br>
“Letting people #engage with their favourite #brand” isn&rsquo;t the same thing.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>If my name was on it forever, would I still be okay with that?</strong><br>
Imagine your resume is a permanent museum exhibit. Is this project in the “career highlights” wing or the “bad decisions” basement?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Would I be proud to talk about it in a job interview five years from now?</strong><br>
Future me is a lot less forgiving than panicked, job-hunting me.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>If I can’t answer “yes” to all of these, I need to decide whether to push back, find another path, or walk away entirely. Once you compromise on ethos, it&rsquo;s way the fuck harder to get it back.</p>
<p><em>(As an aside, my job at 1Password nails a solid 4/4 here. If you want to work somewhere that actually gives a damn about keeping your stuff safe and private, <a href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/1password">why not join us</a>?)</em></p>
<h2 id="when-you-realize-youre-building-the-torment-nexus">When You Realize You&rsquo;re Building the Torment Nexus</h2>
<p>Sometimes you take a job and only later realize the product you’re helping build isn’t something you believe in anymore. Maybe it shifted gradually. Maybe you didn’t ask the right questions before you signed on. Either way, you’ve ended up at TormentNexusCorp™ and now you’ve got a decision to make: <strong>what’s your next move?</strong></p>
<p>Here is what I try to do when I feel that creeping misalignment:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Name it early.</strong> Don’t wait until you&rsquo;re staring at a launch date. Call out your concerns as soon as you see the problem, and be specific.</li>
<li><strong>Talk to decision-makers.</strong> Share your perspective, not as a moral lecture, but as a leader who&rsquo;s worried about the long-term consequences for customers, reputation, and retention.</li>
<li><strong>Keep receipts.</strong> It&rsquo;s a lot harder for people to claim “no one raised this” if you have a paper trail.</li>
<li><strong>Offer alternatives.</strong> Don&rsquo;t just say &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t think we should do this.&rdquo; Coming to the table with &ldquo;we should do <strong>this</strong> instead&rdquo; is infinitely more powerful.</li>
<li><strong>Decide where your line is.</strong> If the direction doesn&rsquo;t change, you have to choose whether you can stay in good faith. Sometimes that means leaving before the thing ships with your name attached to it.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="you-always-have-the-final-word">You <em>Always</em> Have the Final Word</h2>
<center><img src="/your-heart-is-a-weapon.jpg" alt="Your heart is a weapon the size of your fist. Keep fighting. Keep loving."></center>
<p>I can lead through ambiguity. I can lead through hard times. I can lead when the path forward is messy, uncertain, or full of tradeoffs.</p>
<p>What I can’t do is lead a team to build something I don’t believe in.</p>
<p>If you’re in leadership, your team watches what you say and what you don’t say. They’ll take your silence not just as <em>agreement</em> but as <em>endorsement</em>. If you build the Torment Nexus quietly, they’ll believe it’s the kind of thing you’d build loudly.</p>
<p>I love the phrase in the street art photo above and I think about it often. Your voice is just as much a weapon <strong>and you get to choose how you use it.</strong> Speaking up isn’t just about protecting your own integrity. It’s about giving your team permission to do the same.</p>
<p>So ask yourself: If your name was on it forever, would you still be proud to say you helped make it? If the answer’s no, that’s your signal. Don’t wait until you’ve swallowed your integrity to figure out where your line is.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Postscript:</strong></p>
<p>This post was inspired by Mike Montiero&rsquo;s email newsletter entry this week, <a href="https://buttondown.com/monteiro/archive/how-to-not-build-the-torment-nexus/">How To Not Build The Torment Nexus</a>. It&rsquo;s really really good, he&rsquo;s a much better writer than I am, you should read it.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>So You're A Manager Now. Part 2: Performance Management</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now-performance-management/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now-performance-management/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>Struggling reports and quiet high performers both need your attention. Performance management isn’t just for problems.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After my last post <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44745123">made the rounds</a> (hi Hacker News, you spicy little firestorm), one topic came up a whole bunch in the comments: <strong>performance management</strong>. Specifically, how to handle the extremes: the folks who are struggling and the ones who are quietly crushing it. <em>(If you missed Part 1, “<a href="https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now/">So You’re a Manager Now,</a>” that’s where this whole series started.)</em></p>
<p>So let’s talk about both. Because if you’re only focused on one end of the spectrum, you’re missing the point.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="managing-low-performers-its-not-about-being-nice">Managing Low Performers: It’s Not About Being “Nice”</h2>
<p>There’s a difference between being kind and being vague. Too many new managers mistake silence for mercy. “They’re trying hard. I don’t want to hurt their feelings.” So they say nothing until review season rolls around and suddenly it’s a “surprise” that someone’s underperforming.</p>
<p>That’s not kindness. That’s negligence.</p>
<p>Effective performance management starts with clarity. Don’t wait for an official review to start giving feedback. An annual review is the <em>worst</em> possible time to surprise someone. If you see a pattern, speak up early, and do it with honesty and care. If you&rsquo;re a manager who truly cares about your people, there are few worse experiences imaginable than blindsiding someone with hard feedback they didn&rsquo;t see coming. I&rsquo;ve been on both ends of that conversation and trust me, <strong>nobody</strong> wins in that situation.</p>
<p>Avoid vague feedback like “work harder” or “work faster.” That kind of direction only creates confusion and frustration. Instead, be specific. If someone isn’t writing tests, routinely underestimates their work, or leaves PRs sitting unreviewed for days, say so clearly. And if your organization has a career framework or a set of expectations for their level, use it. Point to exactly where they’re falling short so they can see the gap for themselves and start closing it.</p>
<center><img src="https://media4.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExemY1Z2U5ZTJzdXFtdnE4M2VkYTA1NXNybHVybXVicnZnc3NqdWR6aCZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/l2JeijAxh77OfNY6Q/giphy.gif" alt="NO GIGGLING"></center>
<center><small>It's important to set expectations clearly.</small></center><br>
<p>Don’t rely on “vibes” to figure out if someone’s improving. Set measurable, trackable, and achievable goals. Maybe it’s completing 90 percent of their committed sprint work, closing a specific number of story points, reducing escaped bugs, or writing cleaner PRs that don’t need major rewrites. Whatever the goals are, define them clearly, agree on them together, and track progress over time. Make the target visible so both of you know whether it’s being hit.</p>
<p>If someone’s falling short, give them a fair, <strong>timeboxed</strong>  chance to turn things around. That means coaching, regular check-ins, and real support, not just sitting back and hoping for the best. The timebox matters. Your report needs to know exactly how long they have to show improvement, whether that’s 60 days, 90 days, or something else, and what success actually looks like. And if things still don’t improve by the end of that window, you have to be ready to act. It’s not easy, but keeping someone in a role they can’t succeed in doesn’t help them, the team, or you.</p>
<p>You can be honest without being harsh. You can be firm and still compassionate. And you <em>should</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="managing-high-performers-dont-just-let-them-drift">Managing High Performers: Don’t Just Let Them Drift</h2>
<p>High performers often get the opposite treatment. They’re doing fine, so you leave them alone. No complaints, no drama, just smooth sailing. What’s not to love?</p>
<p>The problem is, if you don’t invest in your top performers, you risk losing them. They may not need hand-holding, but they <em>do</em> need to feel seen, challenged, and valued. Turns out “no news is good news” isn’t a great retention strategy.</p>
<p>Start with visibility. Make sure their contributions are noticed, not just by you, but by your peers and leadership. Give them stretch assignments that push them to grow: let them lead projects, mentor others, or explore technical direction. Recognize their work in a way that actually lands. This doesn’t mean praise for praise’s sake, but a clear signal that their effort and impact matter.</p>
<p>No matter how much code someone’s shipping, there’s <em>always</em> room to grow. It’s your job to help them spot those growth areas, especially the ones they can’t see. People can be brutal self-critics, sure, but we’re also great at missing our own blind spots. Maybe they smash at writing code, but can’t explain it to a non-technical stakeholder without everyone’s eyes glazing over. Maybe they’re great at executing but have never been pulled in early to help define the work. Could they run a demo? Present to an exec? Mentor that struggling engineer we talked about earlier? Growth isn’t just “do more,” it’s <em>“make more impact”</em> and you’re the one who helps them figure out how.</p>
<p>And for the love of pants talk to them about what’s next. What does that high-performing Senior Developer want to grow into? Are they leaning toward a Staff or Architect path? Curious about management? Totally unsure and hoping someone will help them figure it out? News flash: <strong>that someone is you</strong>. It’s your job to start that conversation, poke at the possibilities, and help them sketch out what’s ahead. If they’re already thinking about their next move and you haven’t asked, don’t be shocked when they ghost you for the LinkedIn recruiter who did.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="side-note-if-youre-new-to-this-get-a-guide">Side Note: If You’re New to This, Get a Guide</h2>
<center><img src="/dangerous.jpg" alt="it's dangerous to go alone! take this." width="300"></center>
<p>Performance management is hard. It takes judgment, clarity, and a willingness to have uncomfortable conversations. If you&rsquo;re new to this, you&rsquo;re probably second-guessing yourself a lot. That&rsquo;s expected, this shit is <em>not</em> easy and you shouldn&rsquo;t go it alone.</p>
<p>Find a mentor. Someone who’s been through it before. Someone who can gut-check your instincts, help you calibrate expectations, sanity-check your documentation, and give you honest feedback on how you’re showing up. This could be a more seasoned colleague, a former manager from your last gig, or even a stranger on <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/EngineeringManagers/">r/EngineeringManagers</a> who’s a few steps ahead of you. Managing performance is a skill like any other, and it’s way easier to handle when you’ve got someone (or at least a tiny kitten) in your corner.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="performance-management-is-a-leadership-problem">Performance Management Is a Leadership Problem</h2>
<p>If your top performer is quietly burning out while someone else is flailing with no direction, the problem isn’t them. It’s you.</p>
<center><img src="/mirror.jpg" width="300" alt="looking-in-the-mirror meme"></center>
<p>Performance management isn’t just about “fixing” low performers or tossing gold stars at your high ones. It’s about making sure everyone knows where they stand, what’s expected of them, and how they can grow. That takes real clarity, actual support, and the guts to have honest conversations, even when they’re awkward. <em>Especially</em> when they&rsquo;re awkward.</p>
<p>This is part of the job. You don’t get to opt out. If you’re avoiding it, I hate to break it to you but you&rsquo;re not &ldquo;leading.&rdquo; You’re &ldquo;hoping.&rdquo; And in the entire history of business, exactly zero good decisions have been made on hope.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="wrapping-it-up">Wrapping It Up</h2>
<p>Performance management isn’t some checkbox you revisit in a mad dash to get all your reviews written on time once or twice a year. It’s the real, day-to-day work of leadership: helping people grow, course-correct, and do the best work of their careers. That means being honest. That means being consistent. And yeah, that&rsquo;s gonna mean having some uncomfortable conversations along the way.</p>
<p>But when you get it right? People thrive. Teams get stronger. And you stop spending your time putting out fires or wondering why your best folks are quietly disappearing.</p>
<p>So don’t put it off. Don’t hope it’ll sort itself out. Look at what your team needs and go do the thing.</p>
<center><img src="https://media3.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExZ3FobnZuYnZ4cWE0MXNoYWZpZTU3eGNhcDBrdXkwNTA0aHFqNW83ZiZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/NPRgEfb3m39wvuphjI/giphy.gif" alt="go forth my minions!"></center>
<center><small>Nothing feels better than a high-performing team firing on all cylinders.</small></center>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>So You're A Manager Now.</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>Advice for first-time managers from someone who learned it the hard way, cleaned it up, and passed it on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p><strong>Hi, Hacker News!</strong> I&rsquo;m glad you&rsquo;re here! Getting front page&rsquo;d there was unexpected and cool. If you’re here from there, thanks for clicking. Hope you find something useful. Lots of good discussion in the comments there and I&rsquo;m planning some follow up posts Real Soon Now™ on some of the topics brought up (performance management, upward communication, etc.) so stay tuned!</p></blockquote>
<p><em><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/so-youre-a-manager-now-performance-management/">Part 2 of this series is now live</a>. It’s all about performance management: how to support the folks who are struggling, and the ones quietly crushing it.</em></p>
<p>Welcome to the club. You either asked for this, or someone tapped you on the shoulder and said, “Hey, you seem responsible. Wanna be in charge of other humans?” Either way, here you are. Congrats. Or condolences. Maybe both.</p>
<p>Being a first-time manager is weird. You go from being great at your job to being a total beginner at a job that nobody really taught you how to do. There’s no “Manager Bootcamp.” There&rsquo;s no Bachelor&rsquo;s Degree in Engineering Management <em>(ok, actually, there is but they&rsquo;re scams. Just don&rsquo;t.)</em> You’re just… here now.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="your-job-isnt-to-do-the-work-anymore">Your Job Isn’t to Do the Work Anymore.</h2>
<p>I know. That part sucks a little. You were probably really good at your job. Now your job is to make sure other people can be good at <em>theirs</em>. You’re not the player, you’re the coach. Sometimes that means strategy and big-picture thinking. Sometimes it means shielding your team from dumb shit. Sometimes it means buying someone coffee and saying, “You’re not crazy. This <em>is</em> hard.”</p>
<p>You might miss the dopamine hit of pushing a PR or closing a ticket. That’s normal. It can be hard to feel useful when your output is meetings and docs instead of code and commits. But your job now is to build systems, not features. To coach, not to execute. To unblock and enable, not to do it all yourself.</p>
<p>This means you need to <em>trust your team</em> to get the work done instead of doing it yourself. Your instinct (especially under pressure) is going to be to fall back on the skills that got you this far in your career: to jump in, write the code, fix the bug, save the fuckin&rsquo; day. Occasionally a manager will need to dive in and do the ground-level work but that is the exception and not the rule because the reality is you have different <em>critical</em> responsibilities now.</p>
<p>Get comfortable with your impact being less visible but more meaningful.</p>
<center><img alt="What would you say... you do here?" src="https://media2.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExanF2NHJiNXkxMGRjcWcyNXE1M2p1OG1sa3Zza3FlY2p5NWtqOXcybiZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/ToMjGpJ1lQiQarAftaU/giphy.gif"></center>
<center><small>I've been doing management for over a decade and some days I still have no idea.</small></center>
<hr>
<h2 id="youre-going-to-mess-stuff-up-repeatedly">You’re Going To Mess Stuff Up. Repeatedly.</h2>
<p>You’ll give the wrong feedback. Or avoid a tough convo until it explodes. Or be too hands-on. Or not hands-on enough. It’s all part of it.</p>
<p>Nobody expects you to have all the answers. If you expect <em>yourself</em> to have all the answers you&rsquo;re setting yourself up for a heaping dose of reality check the very first time you run into a scenario you&rsquo;re unprepared for.</p>
<p>You’re not expected to be perfect. You <em>are</em> expected to notice when you screw up, own it, and get better. The goal isn’t “flawless.” It’s “fuck up better each time.”</p>
<p>Messing up is part of the job. What matters more is how you respond. Own your mistakes. Say the awkward thing out loud. Apologize when you blow it. Your team doesn’t need a flawless boss, they need a human one who’s willing to grow in public. That builds trust faster than pretending you’ve got it all figured out.</p>
<center><img alt="Be the Dude." src="https://media2.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExNXFjaGp6YmRvdWE5anR4Nzl3dmZmdWx0cTFqN3hpN200ejg4eGMzNSZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/bqalUGFYfyHzW/giphy.gif"></center>
<center><small>You're gonna fuck up. When you do... be The Dude.</small></center>
<hr>
<h2 id="be-clear-painfully-clear">Be Clear. Painfully Clear.</h2>
<p>You think you’re being obvious. You’re not. Spell out expectations. Over-communicate. Set goals in plain language. Be upfront when someone’s struggling, and just as vocal when they’re killing it. Being vague might feel &ldquo;nicer&rdquo; or &ldquo;more collaborative&rdquo; but it&rsquo;s actually just three cowardices in a trench coat.</p>
<p>Clarity is one of the most underrated tools you have. Without it, people spin. They waste time guessing what “done” means, or whether their work matters, or if you’re secretly disappointed in them. Your job is to remove that ambiguity. Define what good looks like. Repeat yourself. Make sure people feel safe asking you to repeat it again.</p>
<p>As a manager one of the most important tasks you have on any given day is this: <strong>provide context</strong>. The people on your team need to have a strong understanding of why their work matters, why what they&rsquo;re doing is important, and how they&rsquo;re measuring up to expectations. If an engineer feels like they&rsquo;re doing pointless busy work that&rsquo;s a sign that <strong>you</strong> haven&rsquo;t done your job correctly.</p>
<p>Nobody ever said, “Gee, I wish my manager had been <em>less</em> clear with me.”</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="you-probably-still-have-a-manager-of-your-own-lets-talk-about-that">You Probably Still Have a Manager Of Your Own. Let&rsquo;s Talk About That.</h2>
<h3 id="got-a-good-boss-follow-their-lead">Got a Good Boss? Follow Their Lead.</h3>
<p>If you lucked into a solid leader above you, you’ve hit the jackpot. Learn from them. <em>Learn from their mistakes</em> (because they will make them). Ask questions. Ask questions about their mistakes! Let them sanity-check your 1:1s or feedback drafts. Tell them when you’re in over your head. Good leaders <em>want</em> to help you level up.</p>
<p>Also? When you have a rough day, they’ll know exactly why it sucks. That alone is gold.</p>
<h3 id="got-a-not-so-good-boss-dont-let-them-turn-you-into-one-too">Got a Not-So-Good Boss? Don’t Let Them Turn You Into One Too.</h3>
<p>If your leader is checked out, incompetent, or toxic, sorry. That’s rough. But don’t let their bad habits shape yours.</p>
<p>Be the kind of manager <em>you</em> wish you had. Find support elsewhere: peers, mentors, communities, even ex-managers you trusted. Set your own standard. And yeah, keep receipts. Just in case.</p>
<p>Bad leadership above you isn’t an excuse to stop giving a shit.</p>
<center><img src="https://media2.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExa2hkNjFoM3VpMjd5anhkMHl0Y2d1anZseWJoZmJqajJleWJtOG94ZyZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/gdWu0t5imxLXcpSMks/giphy.gif" alt="My boss is the one with the problem"></center>
<center><small>Nobody who works for me is ever allowed to say this.</small></center>
<center><small><small>j/k they totally can, and probably do. Often.</small></small></center>
<hr>
<h2 id="protect-your-energy">Protect Your Energy.</h2>
<p>Management is emotionally expensive. You’ll absorb team stress, cross-functional chaos, and your own endless self-doubt. That’s the gig. Your calendar fills up fast, and those blocks aren&rsquo;t just &ldquo;meetings,&rdquo; they&rsquo;re your priorities on full display.</p>
<p>You <em>have</em> to take care of yourself. Whatever that looks like: therapy, journaling, going for a silly little walk, blocking off calendar time to think instead of react. Do that. Often.</p>
<p>Something important to keep in mind here: burnout doesn’t always show up as dramatic exhaustion. Sometimes it sneaks in quiet. You stop caring. You feel numb. You start defaulting to “whatever.” That’s burnout too. Watch for it in yourself <em>and</em> in your team. If you burn out, <strong>your team burns with you.</strong> I&rsquo;ve been on good teams that have crumbled when their manager crashed. <em>I&rsquo;ve been that manager.</em> It sucks.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="your-wins-are-now-your-teams-wins">Your Wins Are Now Your Team&rsquo;s Wins.</h2>
<p>When you were an IC, you probably did some incredible work. Shipped cool features. Fixed nightmare bugs at 2 a.m. Made things people loved. You got the praise, maybe even a shiny award or two. That was nice. Hate to break it to you but those days are over.</p>
<p>Good managers don&rsquo;t get trophies because we&rsquo;re no longer Doing The Things, we&rsquo;re <em>Empowering</em> The Things. There&rsquo;s a reason an Engineering Manager has never won a Webby award.</p>
<p>At my day job we use a platform called <a href="https://bonusly.com/">Bonusly</a> for people to give little shout-outs (shouts-out?) to their peers for doing something awesome. I rarely get any awards here, but people on my teams get them all the damn time and to me that speaks incredible volumes. When I see someone from another team thank one of my ICs for their help or recognizing something they&rsquo;ve done <em>that&rsquo;s a checkmark in my win column too</em> because I&rsquo;m empowering that. I&rsquo;m creating an environment where this happens on the regular.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="final-thought">Final Thought</h2>
<p>You’re not going to get it all right. None of us do. But if you show up with humility, curiosity, and a genuine desire to make work suck less for the people around you? That’s real leadership.</p>
<p>You’ve got this. And even on the days you feel like you don’t, that’s okay too. Welcome to the deep end.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Day The Sugar Didn't Make It</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/the-day-the-sugar-didnt-make-it/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/the-day-the-sugar-didnt-make-it/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>This moment happened almost twenty years ago, but I still think about it whenever I’m leading a team under pressure.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 id="scene-seattle-a-grey-drizzly-wednesday-morning-748-am-pacific-time-interior-of-a-red-pontiac-sunfire">SCENE: SEATTLE. A GREY, DRIZZLY WEDNESDAY MORNING. 7:48 AM PACIFIC TIME. INTERIOR OF A RED PONTIAC SUNFIRE.</h3>
<h3 id="date-march-15-2006">DATE: MARCH 15, 2006</h3>
<p>A young man decides that, on his way to work this morning, a cup of coffee and perhaps a delicious pastry of some sort would certainly not go amiss. It just so happens that his place of work is within rock-throwing distance of no fewer than seven Starbucks locations. He chooses his preferred one; the lineups are usually longer there, but he enjoys the friendliness of the staff. Besides, showing up at work on time this morning isn’t really a priority.</p>
<p>The Starbucks is, as downtown coffee houses often tend to be at 7:52 a.m., a certifiable madhouse. The lineup, as he had surmised, is quite long, but he doesn’t mind. The small army of green-apron-clad soldiers on both sides of the counter are lethally efficient in the way they move and serve customers, so the line moves quickly. As he waits, he lets his gaze wander around the shop.</p>
<p>The garbage receptacles, he notices, are full to overflowing. Every cream dispenser (the standard array: one skim, one whole, and two half-and-half) is empty. There are no sugar packets available. He surmises it must have been busier than usual this morning. Understandable, it’s a little chillier than it has been in recent days. The staff are working hard to keep up with the flow of customers entering through the door. It’s a testament to their skill that drinks are made, served, and enjoyed even in all the bustle.</p>
<p>He approaches the counter and notes, with pleasure, that it’s his favorite server helping him this morning. No matter how busy it is, she’s always smiling. Cheerful, but not annoyingly so at 7:58 a.m. Cute, too. She usually recognizes him, and knows what drink he likes. Venti Americano, room for cream. Cranberry white-chocolate scone on the days they have them. Today, they do.</p>
<p>Something happens as he reaches the counter.</p>
<p>Another server, one he doesn’t recognize, is also working this morning. Is she new? Transferred from another store? Normally works the evening shift? He doesn’t know. This new girl is clearly feeling stressed by the chaos of the morning. She sighs audibly, and then:</p>
<p><em>&ldquo;Fuck this. I’m going on my break.&rdquo;</em></p>
<p>She sets down the box she had been holding and quickly strides into the back room. The sugar packets she was taking to the condiment stand never make it out from behind the counter.</p>
<p>This morning is the first time he’s ever seen his favorite server, the one who’s always cheerful and upbeat, frown.</p>
<p><strong>CUT TO BLACK.</strong></p>
<hr>
<p><em>The coffee was still hot. The pastry was still good. But something invisible had gone out of the room. A shift in tone, a crack in the rhythm.</em></p>
<p><em>Now, years later, I see it for what it was: a small fracture in the team’s trust. Not because someone made a mistake, but because they checked out when it mattered most.</em></p>
<p><em>Moments like that don’t show up on dashboards, but they’re the ones that stick.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>How to Train Your D̶r̶a̶g̶o̶n̶ Manager</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/how-to-train-your-manager/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/how-to-train-your-manager/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>I became a manager by accident. Here's what I wish someone had done for me and how I'm doing it differently for the next generation.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I became a manager by accident.</p>
<p>Not in the &ldquo;oops, I left my desk and came back to a team&rdquo; kind of way, but close. I was a strong IC. I wrote good code, made solid architectural decisions, hit my deadlines, and collaborated well with others. I published articles. I taught university classes in three countries. I won awards: I have multiple Cannes Golden Lions and I <em>definitely</em> built websites you&rsquo;ve used, apps you&rsquo;ve downloaded, and TV commercials you&rsquo;ve watched.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve shipped work for some of the biggest, most recognisable brands in the world. If I checked your closet, your garage, your fridge, and your desk I&rsquo;d almost certainly find logos of companies I&rsquo;ve worked for. I&rsquo;ve had my work prominently displayed in galleries, on billboards, even featured at events in the White House. I was <em>at the fucking top of my industry.</em> And then it all fell apart.</p>
<p>What happened? Someone looked at all that and said to themselfs &ldquo;we should hire this guy and make him a Director!&rdquo; Next thing I knew they threw a lot of money at me and suddenly I was running a team. This team was entirely comprised of people smarter than me.</p>
<p>And I had no idea what I was doing.</p>
<center><img alt="I have no idea what I'm doing" src="https://media4.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExb2JzOWlyYWUzcThqczhhZzZydW5yM29jMHR3cmk0bzdlaTR3Y2UxcCZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/dGk3j2cMR4jao/giphy.gif"></center>
<center><small>Pro tip: if you want to run a successful company <strong>don't do that</strong>.</small></center>
<hr>
<h2 id="trial-by-fire-is-not-a-training-plan">Trial by Fire Is Not a Training Plan</h2>
<p>That first year in leadership was rough. I spent a lot of time pretending I had answers I didn&rsquo;t have, staying up late reading management books I barely understood, and sweating spinal fluid trying to project the impression that I wasn&rsquo;t fifty-eleven leagues out of my depth.</p>
<p>No one really trained me. I was just suddenly &ldquo;in charge.&rdquo; The assumption seemed to be: <em>if you&rsquo;re good at the job, you&rsquo;ll know how to lead others doing it.</em></p>
<center><img alt="That's not how any of this works!" src="https://media1.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExaHBlaXZuMno4aWI4dzloMzdvZnM4czBrYjYwNWd4a2ZxYXpjZXl1ZSZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/r5SxJYcU21Auk/giphy.gif"></center>
<center><small>Hiring the right people is <strong>really hard</strong> as it turns out.</small></center>
<hr>
<h2 id="what-i-wish-id-had">What I Wish I&rsquo;d Had</h2>
<p>Looking back, I don&rsquo;t blame the people who hired me. They were doing their best with what they knew, apparently I talked a good game in the interview, and I went in bright-eyed and bushy tailed trying to do my best to not turn everything around me into a smouldering crater.</p>
<p>I had enthusiasm and ambition but what I <em>really</em> needed was <strong>training</strong>. Mentorship. Space to observe and absorb. Time to develop my own point of view.</p>
<p>I needed someone to say:</p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Here&rsquo;s what changes when you become a manager.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Here&rsquo;s what support looks like now.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Here&rsquo;s what to expect when someone you like starts struggling.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Here&rsquo;s how to give hard feedback without losing the room.&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
<p>I needed someone to walk alongside me while I learned how to lead, and now that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m trying to do differently.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="what-im-doing-differently">What I&rsquo;m Doing Differently</h2>
<p>At my day job we have a role called <em>Team Lead</em> which is essentially a junior Engineering Manager. One of my senior engineers stepped into it recently. They&rsquo;re curious about management, so instead of tossing them into the deep end, we&rsquo;re slow-playing it.</p>
<p>They get to work under an experienced manager <strike>who never makes mistakes</strike> and learn from their mistakes while slowly getting introduced to Manager Lifestyle™.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re doing things like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Giving them exposure to 1:1s <em>before</em> asking them to lead one solo</li>
<li>Letting them shadow performance reviews, then co-write the next one</li>
<li>Talking openly about the emotional weight of leadership — the invisible stuff</li>
<li>Giving space to screw up in low-risk scenarios</li>
<li>Building feedback muscles gradually instead of waiting for a &ldquo;big moment&rdquo;</li>
<li>And most critically important of all: letting <em>them</em> see <em>me</em> screw up</li>
</ul>
<p>The goal isn&rsquo;t to delay their growth. It&rsquo;s to scaffold it.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="a-note-for-the-new-managers-in-the-audience">A Note For The New Managers In The Audience</h2>
<p>Are you a new manager or thinking of becoming one? Here. Come here. Have a seat.</p>
<center><small><img src="https://media4.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTZjMDliOTUyczNja3E5Y2FjbnBpYzZnZWVsajZvZG92NXR1ZzRtMHN4aXZzdDc5MiZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/3xqh9FxO2PpiU/giphy.gif"></small></center>
<p>The scariest part of moving from an IC to Management role is that you suddenly start leaving behind the skills that have made you successful. Your programming skills start moving out of the picture as more of your time becomes invested in people and process.</p>
<p>React can do a lot of things, but it can&rsquo;t help you coach a low-performing engineer out of the weeds. It can&rsquo;t do the work of collaborating with your Product team to plan out next year&rsquo;s roadmap and staffing plan. That&rsquo;s on you and as a new manager you need to learn to flex entirely different muscles you didn&rsquo;t even know you had.</p>
<p>Leadership is a skillset. It&rsquo;s not unlocked with a job title. And it <em>can</em> be taught and it <em>can</em> be learned but only if everyone involved is intentional about how we bring people into it.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve got some words coming for you soon enough, hang tight.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="training-the-next-manager-starts-with-their-current-one-thats-you">Training the Next Manager Starts With Their Current One (That&rsquo;s You)</h2>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in a position of leadership and you see someone on your team with potential, ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
<li>Are you preparing them for the job, or just handing it to them?</li>
<li>Are you giving them feedback, or just responsibility?</li>
<li>Are you normalizing the messiness of leadership, or pretending it&rsquo;s all intuitive?</li>
</ul>
<p>We don&rsquo;t need more accidental managers. We need leaders who were taught, supported, and encouraged to lead with clarity and care.</p>
<p>That starts with us.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Leading Without Non-Negotiables Is Just Damage Control</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/leading-without-non-negotiables/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/leading-without-non-negotiables/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate><description>Why defining your leadership non-negotiables early is critical to leading with integrity and trust.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about non-negotiables lately in both my personal and professional life. With <em>[gestures vaguely]</em> everything going on around us, it&rsquo;s never been more important to draw clear lines in the sand. You have to know where you&rsquo;re flexible, and where compromise simply isn&rsquo;t an option.</p>
<p>As a manager — someone responsible for the care and feeding of nearly twenty humans — this feels even more critical. Leadership is hard. The pressure is constant, the stakes are high, and the demands come from all directions. But here&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;ve learned: if you don&rsquo;t define the values and boundaries you absolutely won&rsquo;t bend, your leadership will be reactionary at best, and at worst, just damage control. Without clear non-negotiables, you risk losing yourself, your team&rsquo;s trust, and ultimately, the ability to lead with integrity. This post is about owning those lines in the sand, early and deliberately, so you can lead with clarity and confidence, even when the pressure hits.</p>
<hr>
<p>One of the things I&rsquo;ve come to believe deeply as a leader is this: <strong>if you don&rsquo;t define your non-negotiables, someone else will define them for you.</strong></p>
<p>That &ldquo;someone&rdquo; might be your company&rsquo;s values (or lack of them), it might be your peers, it might be pressure from above, or it might be burnout, inertia, or fear. But make no mistake, the longer you lead without a compass, the more likely you are to wake up one day doing harm you didn&rsquo;t intend, or tolerating things you would&rsquo;ve once spoken out against.</p>
<p>So I want to talk about leadership non-negotiables, the lines you draw in the sand, early and deliberately, to anchor the kind of leader you intend to be.</p>
<p>Because if you&rsquo;re not careful, the job will shape you in ways you didn&rsquo;t choose.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="what-are-non-negotiables">What Are Non-Negotiables?</h3>
<p>To me, they&rsquo;re not aspirational values. They&rsquo;re not what you <em>hope</em> to do on a good day when things are calm and your team is thriving. They&rsquo;re the things you will <strong>refuse to compromise on</strong>, even under pressure, especially under pressure.</p>
<p>They&rsquo;re the &ldquo;I&rsquo;d rather quit than violate this&rdquo; statements.</p>
<p>They&rsquo;re the moments that show your team, and yourself, who you <em>really</em> are.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="mine-for-example-look-like-this">Mine, for example, look like this:</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>I will not lie to my direct reports.</strong><br>
No spin, no half-truths. I&rsquo;d rather say &ldquo;I can&rsquo;t tell you that yet&rdquo; than manipulate someone&rsquo;s understanding of what&rsquo;s happening.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>I will not value output over psychological safety.</strong><br>
Performance matters, but not at the cost of people&rsquo;s well-being. Unsafe teams burn out. Afraid teams underperform.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>I will not fire someone without giving them a truly fair chance to succeed.</strong><br>
A Performance Improvement Plan should be a real attempt to support growth, not a slow-motion termination notice. If I can&rsquo;t stand behind the fairness of the process, I won&rsquo;t own it.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<h3 id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h3>
<p>When you define these early, and more importantly, declare them, something powerful happens:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>You build <strong>trust</strong> with your team.<br>
People know what to expect from you, even when the news is hard.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You hold yourself <strong>accountable</strong>.<br>
You can&rsquo;t fudge your way out of a hard moment when you&rsquo;ve said, out loud, what kind of leader you are.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You <strong>protect your integrity</strong> when the pressure hits.<br>
And if you stay in leadership long enough, it always does.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3 id="how-to-define-your-own">How to Define Your Own</h3>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not sure where to start, ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
<li>What are the moments in leadership I&rsquo;m most proud of?</li>
<li>When have I felt complicit in something I wasn&rsquo;t comfortable with?</li>
<li>What would I be willing to lose a job over?</li>
</ul>
<p>Write the answers down. Sit with them. Refine them. Three non-negotiables is plenty. Don&rsquo;t aim for perfect, aim for <em>true</em>.</p>
<p>Then say them out loud. To your team. To your peers. To your boss, if you&rsquo;re feeling brave.</p>
<p>Leadership clarity starts with self-honesty.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="one-last-thing">One Last Thing</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s easy to fall into thinking that strong values make you inflexible. But I&rsquo;ve found the opposite to be true.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re clear about your bottom lines, you can lead with more openness, more grace, and more confidence, because you&rsquo;re no longer making every decision from scratch. You&rsquo;ve drawn your lines. You&rsquo;ve said, &ldquo;This is where I stand.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And the people around you? They&rsquo;ll feel it, and trust you more for it.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Thoughts</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/blog/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><description>Welcome to my thoughts! Here you’ll find musings on engineering, management, technology, and whatever else catches my interest.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my thoughts! Here you&rsquo;ll find musings on engineering, management, technology, and whatever else catches my interest.</p>
<hr>
<!-- *More thoughts coming soon...*  -->]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Journey</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/journey/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/journey/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 21:01:45 -0400</pubDate><description>Position Statement Engineering and technology leader with 25 years of experience growing teams, scaling systems, and helping people thrive. Brings technical fluency and organizational insight to build software and teams that last.
Work Experience Full work history available on LinkedIn
Engineering Manager, MSP Program, 1Password NOVEMBER 2023 – PRESENT
Leads a globally-distributed team of full stack software engineers responsible for building and maintaining 1Password’s solution for Managed Service Providers Integral partner in recruiting and hiring across the engineering organization, quintupling my team size in one year as well as enabling multiple hires of all seniority levels in adjacent teams Engineering Manager (Contract), Media.Monks JUNE 2023 - NOVEMBER 2023</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="position-statement">Position Statement</h2>
<p>Engineering and technology leader with 25 years of experience growing teams, scaling systems, and helping people thrive. Brings technical fluency and organizational insight to build software and teams that last.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="work-experience">Work Experience</h2>
<p><em>Full work history available on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/scottkosman/">LinkedIn</a></em></p>
<h3 id="engineering-manager-msp-program-1password">Engineering Manager, MSP Program, <a href="https://1password.com">1Password</a></h3>
<p>NOVEMBER 2023 – PRESENT</p>
<ul>
<li>Leads a globally-distributed team of full stack software engineers responsible for building and maintaining 1Password&rsquo;s solution for Managed Service Providers</li>
<li>Integral partner in recruiting and hiring across the engineering organization, quintupling my team size in one year as well as enabling multiple hires of all seniority levels in adjacent teams</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="engineering-manager-contract-mediamonks">Engineering Manager (Contract), <a href="https://media.monks.com">Media.Monks</a></h3>
<p>JUNE 2023 - NOVEMBER 2023</p>
<p>Led multiple cross-disciplinary engineering teams in the development of a digital solution for commercial real estate transactions at a prominent U.S. bank with a workforce of over 20,000 employees. This solution provided title insurance and property/mortgage services to corporate clients worldwide.</p>
<h3 id="engineering-manager-exos">Engineering Manager, <a href="https://teamexos.com">Exos</a></h3>
<p>JULY 2022 - MAY 2023</p>
<p>Led a team of 8 full-stack software engineers responsible for building and maintaining the Exos Fit mobile applications and underlying infrastructure, which connected over 300,000 eligible members to personalized health, nutrition, fitness and recovery coaches generating over $1MM in revenue as a result of signing top tier clients including Google, Intel, Pfizer, PepsiCo and American Airlines.</p>
<ul>
<li>Collaborated closely with cross-functional colleagues (Product, Data, Design, Marketing), business stakeholders, and executive leadership to roadmap quarterly and annual technical plans and product evolution.</li>
<li>Led major technical initiatives including the implementation of Apple Health/Google Fit fitness tracking and push notifications.</li>
<li>Developed OKRs and KPIs in coordination with executive leadership to align the goals of our engineering organization with the larger business. Defined processes for measuring success, and socialized them with  the wider organization.</li>
<li>Implemented a performance management and career growth framework for engineering team members with a focus on SMART goal setting and individual ownership of professional development.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="engineering-director-contract-double-nines-inc">Engineering Director (Contract), <a href="https://doublenines.co">Double Nines, Inc.</a></h3>
<p>DECEMBER 2021 – JUNE 2022</p>
<p>Provided both software engineering direction and senior-level technical consulting to a rapidly scaling vehicle-sharing startup.</p>
<ul>
<li>Directed 20+ member software development team (full-stack web development, data engineering, QA) through all stages of a project life cycle, oversaw engineering responsibilities for different platforms.</li>
<li>Agile technical lead, guided the team through all sprint ceremonies.</li>
<li>Created and reviewed architecture plans through large-scale rewrites of significant portions of an existing application codebase.</li>
<li>Project-scoped new business efforts, including estimation. Directed developers and delivery managers through new business efforts.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="group-engineering-director-thrillworks-inc">Group Engineering Director, <a href="https://thrillworks.com">Thrillworks, Inc.</a></h3>
<p>MAY 2020 – DECEMBER 2021</p>
<p>Oversaw all operations for a 20+ member engineering team including staffing/recruitment, budget forecasts, alignment within the larger organization, and OKR creation.</p>
<ul>
<li>Heavily involved in new business acquisition. Crafted and presented detailed technological business proposals and technology implementation plans for multiple accounts ranging from sub-$100k to $500k.</li>
<li>Forecast long-term trends and business needs ensuring the team is staffed, trained, and equipped correctly.</li>
<li>Introduced a clear structure of team organization and reporting lines to a formerly very flat organizational hierarchy. Established company-wide best practices in career growth, performance management, and training programs, which resulted in increased reported employee satisfaction and confidence.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="director-of-solution-design-adidas">Director of Solution Design, <a href="https://adidas.com">adidas</a></h3>
<p>FEBRUARY 2016 – DECEMBER 2019</p>
<p>Technical Director on adidas.com. Responsible for oversight of all campaign-related development projects at adidas (web, mobile, and in-store digital display), driving and developing technology strategy and execution.</p>
<ul>
<li>Key counterpart for internal clients (business stakeholders, IT/infrastructure, security, product management) and external partners (advertising/production companies, 3rd party content providers) to ensure smooth technical delivery of websites, applications, and mobile development.</li>
<li>Technical direction for multiple €1MM+ budget projects including vetting and selecting vendors, developing technical roadmaps, fostering seamless collaboration between internal and external business partners for timely, on-budget delivery.</li>
<li>Definition, evolution, documentation and training around internal best-practices and guidelines.</li>
<li>Creation, execution, and revision of detailed project work plans to meet changing needs and requirements.</li>
<li>Supported external development agencies with various adidas technical infrastructures (CRM, deployment, etc.).</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="skills">Skills</h2>
<h3 id="leadership--team-building">Leadership &amp; Team Building</h3>
<ul>
<li>Engineering Leadership &amp; People Management</li>
<li>Cross-Functional Collaboration &amp; Delivery</li>
<li>Coaching New Managers</li>
<li>Organizational Design &amp; Team Health</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="strategy--operations">Strategy &amp; Operations</h3>
<ul>
<li>Agile (Scrum, Kanban)</li>
<li>OKRs / KPI Development</li>
<li>Hiring &amp; Performance Frameworks</li>
<li>Product Delivery Planning</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="technical-oversight">Technical Oversight</h3>
<ul>
<li>Web &amp; Mobile Architecture (React, TypeScript, Node)</li>
<li>Cloud Infrastructure (AWS, GCP)</li>
<li>CI/CD &amp; DevOps Practices (GitHub Actions, Terraform)</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/about/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/about/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 20:34:43 -0400</pubDate><description>Bicycle rider.
Engineering Manager/Technology Leader with 20+ years in the trenches as an entrepreneur, IC, people manager, department head, cheerleader, program lead, and pretty much every other role you can think of (yes, even graphic designer).
Scotch drinker.
Not always in that order.
Hi.
I’m Scott. I lead project teams building websites, applications, and other computery-type things that you can click/tap/touch/swipe/wave at.
It was the heady days of 2001. The dot-com bubble had burst, economies were in the soup, consumer dollars were nowhere to be seen, and it seemed like a really dumb time to get involved in the creative/advertising world of computers.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bicycle rider.</p>
<p>Engineering Manager/Technology Leader with 20+ years in the trenches as an entrepreneur, IC, people manager, department head, cheerleader, program lead, and pretty much every other role you can think of (yes, even graphic designer).</p>
<p>Scotch drinker.</p>
<p>Not always in that order.</p>
<p>Hi.</p>
<p>I’m Scott. I lead project teams building websites, applications, and other computery-type things that you can click/tap/touch/swipe/wave at.</p>
<p>It was the heady days of 2001. The dot-com bubble had burst, economies were in the soup, consumer dollars were nowhere to be seen, and it seemed like a really dumb time to get involved in the creative/advertising world of computers.</p>
<p>I’ve never been much for conventional wisdom.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 20-ish years and I find myself still here, still in the industry, still finding new ways to push the envelope of what’s possible on this “internet” thing. I’ve seen a lot of changes in the landscape – when I started out, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YozC8yFrZKI">the internet was on computers now</a>! Today the internet is everywhere: in your pocket, on your tv, wifi in your Uber. Your fridge knows when you’re out of milk and has Instacart bring more. Software that used to come in boxes on double-digit numbers of floppy disks can now be materialised out of the sky onto your futuristic wrist-computer that was beyond the imagination of the people who wrote <em>Star Trek.</em></p>
<p>That’s what I do: find ways to transcend the cold ones and zeroes of technology and build experiences that real people can reach out and touch. Storytelling. Ten years ago that was accomplished by building a website and hoping to get on the first page of Google. The brave new world of today is a little bit (ok, a LOT) different in that the tools we have and the avenues for communication are radically altered from what we used to know, but one thing hasn’t changed: the human soul has an intense desire to connect with something. I see my work as more than just wrangling code, I see it as providing a conduit for that connection to take place.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>How To Scott</title><link>https://scottkosman.com/post/readme/</link><guid>https://scottkosman.com/post/readme/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 20:18:55 -0400</pubDate><description>What’s All This Then? This is my version of a “Manager README.” The purpose is to introduce myself and give you insight into how I think, how I work, and to answer some questions you might have about me. This is a living document and will change over time as necessary. Keeping it transparent is intentional.
TL;DR I care deeply about people, then product, then process, in that order. I value transparency, context, and feedback. I don’t micromanage and expect you to own your work. You’ll always know where you stand with me. I’m available via Slack and rarely answer phone calls unless it’s urgent. This is a living document and may evolve over time. What This Is Not ❌ It won’t list my expectations of you. ❌ It won’t tell you how to do your job. ❌ It won’t define how any particular project should be run. Important Note This README is unofficial and does not override any formal HR policies or performance management processes.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="whats-all-this-then">What’s All This Then?</h2>
<p>This is my version of a &ldquo;Manager README.&rdquo; The purpose is to introduce myself and give you insight into how I think, how I work, and to answer some questions you might have about me. This is a living document and will change over time as necessary. Keeping it transparent is intentional.</p>
<h2 id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<ul>
<li>I care deeply about <strong>people</strong>, then <strong>product</strong>, then <strong>process</strong>, in that order.</li>
<li>I value <strong>transparency</strong>, <strong>context</strong>, and <strong>feedback</strong>.</li>
<li>I don’t micromanage and expect you to <strong>own your work</strong>.</li>
<li>You’ll always know where you stand with me.</li>
<li>I’m available via Slack and rarely answer phone calls unless it’s urgent.</li>
<li>This is a <strong>living document</strong> and may evolve over time.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-this-is-not">What This Is Not</h2>
<ul>
<li>❌ It won’t list my expectations of you.</li>
<li>❌ It won’t tell you how to do your job.</li>
<li>❌ It won’t define how any particular project should be run.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="important-note">Important Note</h2>
<p>This README is unofficial and does <strong>not</strong> override any formal HR policies or performance management processes.</p>
<p>I make no distinction between full-time, part-time, temporary, or remote employees. My goal is to treat everyone with equal respect and support. If it ever feels like I’m falling short, please let me know.</p>
<h2 id="who-am-i">Who Am I?</h2>
<p>I live in <strong>Halifax, Nova Scotia</strong> with my wife Shannie, my budgie Colonel Drumstick, and my cockatiel Coolwhip. I grew up in the Edmonton, Alberta area and have since lived in the USA, Netherlands, Sweden, Germany, and now back in Canada. I’m a sports fan, comic book geek, video game player, electronics tinkerer, hobbyist athlete, and craft beer enthusiast. My pronouns are he/him/his.</p>
<p>I used to be highly extroverted, but I&rsquo;ve grown more introverted with time.</p>
<p>Professionally, I started as a graphic designer in 2001 and quickly learned two things:</p>
<ol>
<li>I was bad at design.</li>
<li>I loved coding.</li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve worked primarily in frontend web development, particularly in the advertising agency space. Over the years, I’ve moved into hybrid IC/management roles, and now I focus mostly on people and teams, though I still dabble in code.</p>
<p>I’m what you might call a <a href="https://tidyfirst.substack.com/p/paint-drip-people">Paint-Drip</a> person. Broad, shallow experience in many areas: backend dev, CI tools, animation, video production, project management, and more.</p>
<p>There’s plenty I’ll learn from you, and I hope I bring things you&rsquo;ll learn from me, too.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-care-about">What I Care About</h2>
<p><strong>In order of priority:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>👥 People</li>
<li>📦 Products</li>
<li>⚙️ Process</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="people">People</h3>
<p>We are all complex, individual human beings. I strive to honor that complexity. I have <em>zero</em> tolerance for harassment or discrimination of any kind (sex, race, orientation, religion, gender identity, etc.).</p>
<h3 id="products">Products</h3>
<p>We need to care deeply about the quality of what we deliver. Working in digital is powerful. We shape how the world sees our company and our work.</p>
<h3 id="process">Process</h3>
<p>Process exists to support people and products, not the other way around. You were hired because you&rsquo;re good at what you do. Speaking up to improve our ways of working is not only welcome, it&rsquo;s expected.</p>
<h2 id="what-you-can-expect-from-me">What You Can Expect From Me</h2>
<ul>
<li>I will prioritize your well-being over output.</li>
<li>I will create space for your ideas, feedback, and growth.</li>
<li>I will advocate for you when you&rsquo;re not in the room.</li>
<li>I will give you honest answers and never lie to you.</li>
<li>I will take your success personally.</li>
<li>I will own and learn from my mistakes.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-role-as-i-see-it">My Role, As I See It</h2>
<h3 id="1-attract-hire-and-retain-the-best-people">1. Attract, hire, and retain the best people</h3>
<p>If you’re reading this, you’re part of that mission.</p>
<h3 id="2-provide-context">2. Provide context</h3>
<p>You should always understand how your work connects to larger goals, OKRs, and priorities. If something feels like pointless busywork, that’s on me. Either I haven’t provided context, or we need to reevaluate the work.</p>
<p>Let me know if that ever happens. It helps us both.</p>
<h2 id="communication">Communication</h2>
<h3 id="my-preferences">My Preferences</h3>
<ul>
<li>💬 In person</li>
<li>💬 Slack</li>
<li>📲 SMS / WhatsApp</li>
<li>🕳️ [gap] Email</li>
<li>🏞️ [Grand Canyon-sized gap] Anything else</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="phone-calls">Phone Calls</h3>
<p>Not listed above for a reason. If my phone rings, I assume it’s an emergency. I use it sparingly and answer accordingly.</p>
<h3 id="response-time">Response Time</h3>
<p>I’m almost always available on Slack during <strong>Atlantic Standard Time</strong> business hours. For anything requiring action, send a DM with a clear ask—don’t rely on tags in issue trackers, as I get too many notifications. My calendar is often quite full, but if something is crucial, send me a Slack DM, mark it urgent in whatever way feels appropriate, and I’ll make time for you as soon as I can.</p>
<p>If you want me to see a ticket, <strong>drop a link to it in Slack</strong>.</p>
<h3 id="after-hours">After Hours</h3>
<p>Sometimes I work evenings or weekends. Unless something is marked urgent, I do <strong>not</strong> expect you to respond outside business hours.</p>
<p>The <strong>exception</strong>: if I phone you, it’s urgent.</p>
<h2 id="feedback">Feedback</h2>
<p>Feedback is foundational. I expect to give it, receive it, and encourage it in all directions.</p>
<p>My #1 goal is for you to be <strong>happy</strong>, <strong>fulfilled</strong>, and doing <strong>great work</strong>. You should never hesitate to bring feedback, concerns, or challenges to me.</p>
<h2 id="one-on-ones-1-1s">One-on-Ones (1-1s)</h2>
<p>These meetings are important to me, and I will <strong>always make time</strong> for them (barring travel, vacation, illness, etc.).</p>
<h3 id="what-to-expect">What to Expect</h3>
<ul>
<li>They’re <strong>your</strong> meetings.</li>
<li>Bring anything you want: questions, frustrations, feedback, ideas.</li>
<li>Not required to be status updates.</li>
<li>Feel free to share agenda items ahead of time if context helps.</li>
</ul>
<p>If something is urgent, don’t wait for the 1-1. Just ping me.</p>
<h2 id="performance-management--model">Performance Management (🚦 Model)</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Note: This is <strong>unofficial</strong> and separate from HR processes.</p></blockquote>
<p>I use a simple internal mental model to track performance:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>🦎 Green</strong>: You’re doing great. I’m thrilled you’re on the team.</li>
<li><strong>🐝 Yellow</strong>: Something&rsquo;s not working long term. Let’s fix it together.</li>
<li><strong>🦀 Red</strong>: A serious concern needs immediate correction to continue on the team.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="important">Important:</h3>
<ul>
<li>You will <strong>never</strong> be surprised by a change in status.</li>
<li>If I haven’t said otherwise, assume you’re <strong>Green</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Ask me</strong> if you’re ever unsure. I won’t mislead you.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="a-word-on-pips">A Word on PIPs</h2>
<p>Performance Improvement Plans (PIPs) are often misused as HR cover before firing someone. I <strong>hate</strong> that.</p>
<p>We all have ups and downs. A PIP, in my view, is a <strong>course correction</strong>, not a death sentence. I’ve helped people through PIPs back to great performance. If it ever comes to that, we’ll face it together with honesty and support.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-think-i-do-well">What I Think I Do Well</h2>
<ul>
<li>✅ Provide context without control. (Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OqmdLcyES_Q">this fantastic ten-minute video</a> to understand more about this philosophy.)</li>
<li>✅ Understand and advocate for customer needs.</li>
<li>✅ Avoid micromanagement.</li>
<li>✅ Build trust and psychological safety.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-i-think-i-dont-do-well">What I Think I Don’t Do Well</h2>
<ul>
<li>❌ I’ve sometimes leaned too hard into &ldquo;context without control&rdquo; and waited too long to step in when someone was struggling. I’ve learned to stay more attuned and offer support sooner.</li>
<li>❌ Haven’t written production-grade code in a long time. Expect to know more than me here.</li>
<li>❌ Historically struggled to say “no” to requests. Still working on this.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="lets-talk">Let’s Talk</h2>
<p>I’d love your thoughts on this README. What’s helpful? What’s missing? How can we make working together even better?</p>
<p>My door (virtual) is open.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>